Guide to the Rice University Faculty Women's Club records, 1920-2016 UA 127
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Faculty Women's Club records
1920-2016
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University Faculty Women's Club.
UA 127
5.5 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
0.416015625 Gigabytes Nearline access: UA0127aip_001 (0.416015625 GB)
Minutes, records, correspondence, photographs and other materials documenting the social and charitable activities of the Rice University Faculty Women's Club.
Biographical / Historical
Begun in the academic year 1920/21, the club served to introduce new faculty wives to the Rice Institute (there were no female faculty members at that time). Later the club also included women faculty members. The Club has served to welcome new women and families to Rice by providing a social venue in an academic setting. Club members were also involved in charitable activities, such as sewing for the Red Cross, knitting blankets for Ben Taub Hospital, as well as having activities for Rice students and parties for faculty children and for club members. At various times in the club's history, interest groups included Arts and Crafts, Bridge, Conversational English for International Students, Play Reading, Psychology, Spanish, French, German, Community Service Handicrafts, Gourmet, Museum Study, Ice Skating, Swimming, Tennis, Rice Tutoring Project Supervisors (of Rice students tutoring elementary school children) each of which planned various programs relevant to their interests. They met for coffees, barbecues, Easter Egg hunts, Christmas dances, and various programs related to their interests groups, often at Cohen House or at the homes of the various members.
The club made donations to the Fondren Library in memory of club members and faculty members who passed away. A Loan Closet was also maintained by the members for the benefit of the International graduate students, who were invited to borrow household items from the closet for the duration of their studies at Rice. Occasionally, the club was a recipient of gifts such as silver, china, trays, bowls, china, and a samovar.
Scope and Contents
Minutes, records, correspondence, invitations, photographs, oral histories and other materials documenting the social and charitable activities of the Rice University Faculty Women's Club. The speakers and menus for the various programs and activities are noted, as well as names of persons memorialized. Directories and other lists often offer the members' married names as well as their given first names.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research, with the execption of boxes 6, 9, and 10 (2012-2013 minutes and correspondence, 2010-2016) which is restricted from any access until 2024.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
Donated by members Elva Gordon, Nancy Boothe, Lorraine Dessler, Ruth Pfeiffer, Frances Brotzen, Kathy Austin, and Mary Dix, over the years 1972, 1983, 1991, 1997, and 2006.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Social life and customs
Document Types
photographs; constitutions; corrrespondence; minutes (administrative records); oral histories (document genres); directories; invitations
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University Faculty Women's Club.
- Series I: Minutes, notes, calendars and correspondence, 1920-2008, 239512
  - 1920/21-1943/44, 239544 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1944/45-1951/52, 239543 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1952/53-1955/56, 239542 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1955/56-1959/60, 239541 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1960/61-1962/63, 239540 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1963/64, 239539 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1964/65-1965/66, 239538 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1966/67, 239537 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1967/68, 239536 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1968/69, 239535 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1969/70, 239534 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1970/1971 (includes 50th anniversary luncheon menu, planning, and comments by Ms. Tsanoff and Ms. Belle Heaps), 239533 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1971/72, 239532 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1972/73 – 1974/75, 239531 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1975/76 – 1976/77, 239530 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1977-78, 239529 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1970/80-1980/81, 239528 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1984/85 – 1985/86, 239527 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1986/87, 239526 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 1987/88, 239525 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 1988/89, 239524 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - 1989/90, 239523 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 1990/91 (includes photographs of tour of Masters' houses, and of the Club board), 239522 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1991/92 (includes photographs of various meetings), 239521 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 1992/93, 239520 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 1993/94, 239519 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 1994/95, 239518 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 1996/97 (includes photographs of various meetings), 239517 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 1997/98, 239516 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 1998/99, 239515 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - 1999/2000 – 2001-2002, 239514 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 2002/03 – 2004/05, 2007-2008, 239513 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Series II: Oral histories, memoirs, memorials, 1950-1997, 239499
  - Club history notes by Gertrude Bray, 1976 and 1982, 239511 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Oral history interview transcripts and cassette tapes, 1989-1997; 239502 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Conditions Governing Access
    These interviews do not have signed consent forms and therefore cannot be placed publicly online at this time. They are available in digital mp3 format by request via the Woodson Research Center.
    - Louise Camden interviewed by Virginia Rorschach (wife of Carroll Camden, English), April 14, 1989, 239509
      - Transcript, audiocassette, digital audio on CD, 239510 (Box 4, Folder 4a)
    - Edythe Fulton (wife of J. Street Fulton, Philosophy) interviewed by Virginia Rorschach (wife of Carroll Camden, English), March 22, 1989, 239507
      - Transcript, audiocassette, digital audio on CD, 239508 (Box 4, Folder 4b)
    - Marian Williams interviewed by Lorraine Dressler, May 30, 1989, 239505
      - Transcript, audiocassette, digital audio on CD, 239506 (Box 4, Folder 4c)
    - Rice University Women's Club, April 9, 1997, 50 years, Demaris Hudspeth, Nancy Akers, Ruth Pfeiffer, 239503
      - Transcript, audiocassette, digital audio on CD (2cd's), 239504 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Memoirs and photographs, 1979-1997, 239501 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Memorials, 1950s-1996, 239500 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series III: Constitution, directories, and club guide, 1948-1989, 239495
  - Constitutions, 1948-1985, 239498 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Directories, 1961-1989 (see also Series I: Minutes, notes, calendars and correspondence for more informally produced directories), 239497 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Guide for Faculty Families", 1962; 239496 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series IV: Events and programs, 1982-1997, 239491
  - Emeritus Coffee, 1982, 239494 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reading group, 1984-1997. Includes names of chairpersons and members, books read, and photographs of members., 239493 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 75th Anniversary celebration, April 10, 1996 (booklet, correspondence, photographs), 239492 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series V: Treasury and property records, 1931-2005, 239485
  - Treasury book, 1949/50-1958/59, 239490 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Treasury book, 1959/60 – 1970/71, 239489 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Jewelry orders, 1985-2005 (includes order forms, correspondence, 3 brass owl pins), 239488 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Inventory of gifts to and property of Club, 1931-1990, 239487 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Loan Closet, 1990-1991, 239486 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series VI: Minutes, correspondence and directory, 2013-2014, 239482
  Conditions Governing Access note
  This material is restricted from any use until 2024 by request of the donor.
  - Directory, 2012-2013, 239484 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Meetings minutes and correspondence, 2013-2014, 239483 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Series VII: Photography and Book Group, 239473
  - Photography 1995-2001, 239481 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photography 2008-2009, 239480 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Photography 2010-2011, 239479 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Photography: Holiday Party, 2-9-11, 239478 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Photography: Centennial Tea, 5-8-12 and Easter Egg Hunt, 239477 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Photography 2012-2013, 239476 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Photography: Rienzi Tour, 3-14-2014, 239475 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Book Group, 1986-2011, 239474 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series VIII: Addenda, 1997-2016
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes treasurer records, minutes, member list and member information, event information for the years 1997-2016.
  This material is open for research, with the execption of boxes 6, 9, and 10 (2012-2013 minutes and correspondence, 2010-2016) which is restricted from any access until 2024.
  - 1997-98 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1998-99 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 2000-01 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 2001-02 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - 2002-03 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 2003-04 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 2004-05 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 2006-07 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 2007-08 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 2008-09 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 2009-10 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - 2010-11 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 2011-12 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 2012-13 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 2013-14 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - 2014-15 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
  - 2015-16 (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Series IX: Addenda FYE 2012
  - Meeting Agendas, 2011-2012 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Membership, 2011-2012 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Events, 2011-2012 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Bylaws, 2011 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Meeting Minutes & Notes, 2011-2012 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Financial, 2011-2012 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Centennial Committee, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Inventory /Correspondence, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Centennial Story Project Faculty Women's Club DVD's, 2012 (Box 11, Folder 9)